<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wp_surface_suspension_v1">
<!-- wrap:70 -->

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2021 Joshua Ashton

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Surface suspension protocol">
    This protocol provides the ability for clients to know when their surfaces
    are suspended or resumed via a pair of events indicating surface
    suspension and resumption suspension states.

    Surfaces start out in the resumed suspension state at creation.

    Surfaces may be put into the suspended state by a compositor issuing
    the suspended event when the compositor believes they are likely not
    to be sent any frame callbacks soon.
    Surfaces in suspended state must not be sent any wl_surface.frame events.

    Surfaces may be put into the resumed suspension state by a compositor issuing
    the resume event.
    Surfaces in resumed state may be sent wl_surface.frame events.

    Subsurfaces are not affected by their parent surface's suspension state.
    
    Client apps and their windowing/graphics APIs can listen to these events and
    handle surface suspension accordingly (eg. releasing graphics resources
    such as buffers or suspending work relating to rendering.)
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_surface_suspension_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface suspension manager">
      The surface suspension manager is a singleton global object that
      provides the ability to create wp_surface_suspension_v1 for a
      given wl_surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the surface suspension manager">
        Destroy the surface suspension manager.

        Child wp_surface_suspension_v1 objects are not affected
        by the destruction of their suspension manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface_suspension">
      <description summary="get a surface suspension object">
        Create a surface suspension interface for a given wl_surface object.
        See the wp_surface_suspension_v1 interface for more details.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_surface_suspension_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_surface_suspension_v1" version="1">
    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the surface suspension object"/>
    </request>

    <event name="suspended">
      <description summary="surface suspension event">
        This event is sent whenever a surface has been suspended.

        This puts the surface into the suspended suspension state.

        If the surface is currently suspended at the time of the surface
        suspension object's creation, this event will be fired immediately.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="resumed">
      <description summary="surface resumption event">
        This event is sent whenever a surface has been resumed.

        This puts the surface into the resumed suspension state.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>

</protocol>
